All right, בוקר טוב *boker tov*, today's דף daf *daf* is ס״ו
*samech vav* and we pick up on the bottom of ס״ה עמוד
ב׳ *samech heh amud beis*, the two lines תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan.
*tana rabanan*. We just discussed the shift that דם בתולים dam betulim
*dam betulim* in the משנה *mishnah* was a basis for being lenient,
but at the time of רב *Rav* and שמואל *Shmuel* began an
approach, not yet completely solidified, but got solidified later and in the
post-גמרא Gemara *Gemara* period that always treat דם בתולים dam betulim *dam
betulim* as if it were דם נדה Niddah *dam niddah*. Just two
final comments about that. First, an interesting point which is that there
was always a מנהג minhag *minhag* recorded in a ספר *sefer* called
חילוקים בין בני מזרח לבני מערב *Chilukim Bein Bnei Mizrach Livnei Ma'arav*,
which was a גאוני *Geonic*, an early גאוני *Geonic* work which actually
recorded practice differences between communities in Israel and in בבל Bavel? *Bavel*,
which sometimes parallels debates between the בבלי Bavli. *Bavli* and ירושלמי Yerushalmi
*Yerushalmi*. Anyway, it speaks about a practice already way back of women
manually rupture their hymen before the wedding night, which is interesting because
there's other גמרות Gemaros, *Gemoras* that specifically talk about, you know, we
didn't even say why is the משנה *mishnah*, for example, referring to
the first act of sex as ביאת מצוה *bias mitzvah*? That's come
up a few times, we did discuss that. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos*
says it's because that act which a woman's body changes in connecting
to her husband, you know, is sort of is considered to be
a very profound act, you know, that's when she if you would
like becomes a woman in that physical sense, sexual, and transforms into
a sexual being, you know, at least in that for the physical
sense.
So that's what תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos* emphasizes why it's called ביאת מצוה
*bias mitzvah*. It should be noted by the way, again a little
note, not תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* here, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* in כתובות *Kesubos*.
I should note by the way that that doesn't mean that the
couple has to have sex the wedding night itself. That's just the
first act of sex when it occurs and sometimes the couple isn't
ready to have sex the wedding night, definitely a side point. Anyway,
back to this point, given that background it's interesting to note that
there was this practice for women actually to manually, you know, tear
their hymen so as and it is interesting because nowadays in terms
of the challenges that דם בתולים Dam Betulim *dam betulim* presents that
the couple has to separate right after they have sex on the
wedding night, some women actually do opt to go to a gynecologist
and have their hymen removed so that they don't have to deal
with the דם בתולים Dam Betulim *dam betulim*.
And then they don't have to separate?
Correct. If there's no hymen, if the hymen has been surgically removed
or if the woman isn't a virgin, then these הלכות halachot *halachos*
don't apply.
Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it's grounds for divorce though right?
למה תצא היא וכתובתה *lema tetzei hi u'kesuvatah*? Well, that depends, well,
it depends on the context and depends whether the husband is aware
and all of that. That's the thing. Anyway, so that's an interesting
footnote. And the other thing I'll point out is, you know, is
the just clarify, which I'll send out on the listserv, you know,
Michael's point, Michael clarified the point that the ruling he got was
not that you don't have to worry if there's no blood because
although in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that might be true, in the
time of the ראשונים Rishonim, *Rishonim* and certainly שולחן ערוך *Shulchan Aruch*
and פוסקים *Poskim* it gets completely sort of agreed that even with
no blood, which just shows how far we've gotten from the fact
that if there is blood you can not worry about it and
assume hymenal was the point that even if there's no blood, if
there's been that first act of sex, you have to treat it
as if there was blood and as if it was uterine blood
and so on. But that's only when there's like גמר ביאה *gmar
biah*, full penetration. If it isn't full penetration, it's only when you
actually see blood. So whatever Michael was sharing yesterday was if some,
sometimes, you know, on their wedding night if the couple's inexperienced, they're
not even aware whether they've achieved penetration or full penetration and in
those circumstances if there's no blood and if they don't know if
they've achieved full penetration, then they don't have to worry about it.
But if there is full penetration or once there's blood, then that
of course becomes this הלכה halacha, *halacha* about how דם בתולים Dam
Betulim *dam betulim* becomes now a basis for the woman becoming a
נדה Niddah *niddah* the first time they have sex. Yes.
Just because you don't know for sure.
You don't know for sure and you haven't seen blood, you don't
have to worry about it.
Just if he holds if you want no blood he'd separate how
does surgery on the hymen help?
That's when the woman is does is is a בתולה *besulah* and
does have her hymen intact. Then the fact that the act of
sex could cause rupturing of the hymen, then even if you had
that act of sex, even if you didn't see blood, etc. But
if she's not a בתולה *besulah* or doesn't have her hymen intact,
then you don't have to worry about it. Okay, moving on. Now
that's so that's a whole fascinating הלכה halakhah? *halacha*. We will see
today's דף daf *daf* is going to be more dense in laws,
relevant laws of הלכות נדה hilchot niddah. *hilchos niddah* than probably we've
done for an entire month. So let's take a look. Okay, תנו
רבנן *tana
rabanan*, first wide line now on ס״ה עמוד ב׳ *samech heh amud
beis*. כולן שהיו שופעות דם ובאות מתוך ארבעה לילות אחר ארבעה לילות
מתוך לילה אחר לילה *kulan shehayu shofos dam uba'os mitoch arba leilos
achar arba leilos mitoch lailah achar lailah*. So there are various women
based on the age and whether they've had their period or not,
as we know, that either the first four times that they have
sex they can assume hymenal bleeding, this is now bracketing our practice
and going back to the משנה *mishnah*, or the first night that
they have sex they can assume hymenal bleeding. What happens if the
bleeding continued from those four nights to after those four nights or
from the first night to after it, you know, depending on what
the allowance is? כולן צריכות לבדוק את עצמן *kulan tzerichos livdok et
atzman*. They all have to check themselves. So what are they—what are
they checking themselves?
That they can't just say, "Oh, you know, I'm continuing to bleed,
therefore obviously it's still hymenal bleeding." They have to check the bleeding
that occurs afterwards, even though it's sort of from before—the period before—and
to make sure that at least it looks—we'll see in a minute—that
it looks similar to the bleeding before in terms of the color
and whatever, if they want to rely that this bleeding after is
a continuation of the allowance of the bleeding from before. וכולן,
in all these cases, רבי מאיר מחמיר כדברי בית שמאי. Rabbi Meir
machmir kedivrei Beit Shammai. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is strict like בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. He doesn't give four nights and one night; he
would give one night and the first act of sex, right? בית
שמאי Beit Shammai always gives a lesser allowance. ושאר ימים שבין בית
שמאי ובין בית הלל הלך אחר מראה דמים. U'shear yamim shebein Beit
Shammai uvein Beit Hillel, halach achar mareh damim.
And all the other sort of times of seeing between בית שמאי
Beit Shammai and בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you know, they debate again,
four nights, one night, one night, the first time, etc. You have
to go and you look at what the blood looks like. Now,
what does that mean? That means that even when רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir is being strict like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, he actually would
say, one minute, let me just check רש"י Rashi a minute. Right,
that רבי
מאיר,
Rabbi Meir,
even though רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is being strict like בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, for example, בית הלל Beit Hillel would say you have
four nights in certain cases and בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say
you only have one night, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would actually
be sometimes lenient and say, you know what? Even if it's after
that one night of בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, if the blood that
you're seeing after that night looks like the blood you saw during
that night, that would be a basis for being lenient. So basically,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai himself just gives a very limited amount of
time—one night, the first act of sex, or whatever—and for him, except
in the exceptional case when the bleeding is continuous, he doesn't care
even if the blood afterwards looks like the blood during. He's not
going to be lenient after his small allowance of time. רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, however, although he's strict like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, would
give greater allowance when the blood after appears like blood during. Okay,
so what we're seeing here is number one, a partial ruling according
to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, and more,
what we're seeing is the idea that when the appearance is the
same, it's a basis for being lenient, if the flow continues or
maybe to be more lenient than בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר
מראה דמים משונים הם זה מזה, Shehaya Rabbi Meir omer mareh damim
meshunim hem zeh mizeh, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used to say
that the way the blood—the different appearances of blood, whether you're dealing
with hymenal bleeding or menstrual bleeding—are different from one another. כיצד, Keitzad,
how is that true? דם נידה אדום דם בתולים אינו אדום. Dam
nida adom, dam betulim eino adom. נידה Nida blood is red, hymenal
bleeding blood is not red. I don't know what he means by
"not red." I mean, it is red, but maybe it means like
it's a brighter red, not a darker red. It certainly is a
different color. You know, it's just a straight blood, basically. דם נידה—right,
Dam nida I mean, menstrual bleeding is the whole lining of the
uterus, it's got a lot more things than just blood going on
there, so the color is definitely different than the straight bright red
of a wound. דם
נידה זהום דם בתולים אינו זהום. Dam nida zehum, dam betulim eino
zehum. נידה Nida blood is smelly, and not בתולים betulim blood, for
a similar reason. דם נידה בא מן המקור דם בתולים בא מן
הצדדים. Dam nida ba min hamakor, dam betulim ba min hatzdadim. And
here actually is the difference: that נידה nida blood comes from the
uterus, דם בתולים comes from literally the sides, meaning from this—from the
hymen, not from the—you know, in the vaginal canal and not from
the uterus. Okay, so what we have now here introduced is the
interesting sort of observation about the differences of the nature and the
source of these bloods, and therefore another factor to consider—and this, Rachel,
is the point you raised yesterday—is are we dealing with hymenal bleeding
or uterine bleeding? It's not just how old is the girl and
this and that, but other evidence. And here, one very important evidence
is let's look at the blood and try to get an assessment
based on that. Okay, אמר רבי יצחק
בר רב יוסף אמר
רבי יוחנן:
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Rav Yosef amar Rabbi
Yochanan:
only, you know, if you actually see it coming out of you
or is—let's say—if it's on a—something else?
If it's a stain, it's much more lenient because of all the
הלכות halachot of כתמים. ketamim. This is even if she is already—even—אמר
רבי יצחק בר רב יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן זו דברי רבי מאיר.
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Rav Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan: Zu divrei Rabbi
Meir. That's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, which seemed very logical. וחכמים אומרים
כל מראה דמים אחת הן. Vachachamim omrim: Kol mareh damim achat hen.
They all look the same. Which doesn't—I don't know if they meant
that they really say that it all looks the same or they
basically say, treat it the same. It's not enough of a basis
to make this assessment based on—and again, there you go, Rachel, that
goes to a move to much more sort of
formalistic—you know—positions: how old is the girl, this that or whatever, four
days, one night, and so on, rather than a case-by-case assessment which
might be, on the one hand, more accurate but, on the other
hand, it's—you know—it's sort of less—you know—clearly defined, less
quantifiable. And that—there often is that halachic move to more—you know—to sort
of more formal and quantifiable types of criteria. Okay. תנו רבנן. That's
the end of דם בתולים issue. Now we get—move on to a
related but actually a new topic, which is very important for other
הלכות of נידה. nida. So let's take a look. הרואה דם מחמת
תשמיש. Haroeh dam machamat tashmish. A woman sees blood during the act
of sex. Now, until now we were assuming oh, it's because of
the— It's the first time and it'll bleed. But now we've got
a situation, it's in the middle of a marriage, it has nothing
to do with the first time. So now we've got a problem.
She's bleeding as a result of sex. So the first thing would
be, okay, have her see a doctor. There's probably some irritation going
on, right? And to some degree the גמרא Gemara is going to
consider that, but to some degree the גמרא Gemara is more concerned
that maybe the sex is bringing on actual נדה Niddah bleeding. And
then you've got a big problem because if every time they have
sex she bleeds and you think it might be נדה niddah. bleeding,
then how is this couple going to stay together? Okay, so let's
take a look. הרואה דם מחמת תשמיש, Haroah Dam Machmat Tashmish, משמשת
פעם ראשונה ושניה ושלישית. meshameshet pa'am rishona ushniya ushlishit. She can have
sex three times. Even if it occurs once or twice, she can
have sex three times because until it's three times, you don't have
to worry about it. That's the idea of חזקה. Chazakah. מכאן ואילך
לא תשמש עד שתתגרש. Mikan va'eilach lo tishamesh ad shetitgaresh.
Afterwards, she can no longer have sex unless she gets divorced. And
then it's not with the same guy. She can't continue having sex
with the same guy because we have to assume, she has sex
with somebody else? Yes, we'll talk about that. Right, we assume that
it might depend on the person. And also, right, I mean if
you have a big man and a small woman or whatever, I
mean there could be realities that cause this type of irritation and
so on. So the thing is though, we'll discuss in a minute,
what, there's no way to try to save this marriage? So we'll
talk about that in a minute. But for now it says she
has to be afraid that the sex is bringing on bleeding and
that it's נדה niddah. bleeding, not מכה makkah bleeding, not wound-based, and
therefore she has to marry another person. She has to get divorced
from this guy. Top of ס״ו עמוד א׳. Samech Vav Amud Aleph.
ותנשא לאחר Vetinnasei leachair
and marry somebody else. נשאת לאחר, Nisseit leachair, she marries another guy,
וראתה דם מחמת תשמיש, vera'atah dam machmat tashmish, and it's happening again,
bleeding as a result of sex. משמשת פעם ראשונה ושניה ושלישית, meshameshet
pa'am rishona ushniya ushlishit, have sex three times. First two times we
say well maybe it's a freak occurrence and the third time, now
it's a pattern.
מכאן ואילך לא תשמש עד שתתגרש, Mikan va'eilach lo tishamesh ad shetitgaresh,
she
can't continue having sex with this guy
until she gets divorced and only now with a new guy. ותנשא
לאחר Vetinnasei leachair and marry somebody else. נשאת לאחר, Nisseit leachair, she
marries a third guy, וראתה דם מחמת תשמיש, vera'atah dam machmat tashmish,
again she's bleeding as a result of sex, משמשת פעם ראשונה ושניה
ושלישית, meshameshet pa'am rishona ushniya ushlishit,
one and two and she can have, she can have sex a
third time because until it happens three times, it might not be
a pattern. מכאן ואילך לא תשמש עד שתבדוק עצמה. Mikan va'eilach lo
tishamesh ad shetivdok atzmah. Now she's really stuck. Why is she stuck?
Because
as is implicit in this and the גמרא Gemara is going to
make explicit, the reason she can marry another guy is it might
be based on the guy, not totally based on her. So therefore
the problem now is though she's not only established a pattern that
with each person she's got a pattern, but she has it with
three different men. So now it's not, now we're going to assume
it's not based on the man, it's just based on her. So
now she can't have sex with anybody because we've had three different
men and it still happened. So now we have to try to
find other ways to prove that this is not uterine bleeding, but
it's some type of מכה makkah wound-based bleeding and therefore to say
it's no longer going to be a problem. Okay, so we'll talk
about that in a minute, but let's first see what the test
is.
She has to check herself. כיצד בודקת את עצמה? Keitzad bodakat et
atzmah? How does she check herself? מביאה שפורפרת, Meviah shoferet, she brings
a
tube, ובתוכה מכחול, uvtochah michol, and in
it is a מכחול, michol,
which is like an eyelash applicator, like a stick is inside of
a hollow tube, ומוך מונח על ראשה, umoch munach al roshah, and
there is a pad on top of the applicator, you know, on
the head of the applicator that's in the tube. Okay, so basically
the tube is inserted into the woman, and then the applicator is
inserted through the tube and it touches what? Q-tip. Q-tip, what?
Yeah, and it's inserted all the way up until it touches the
uterus. So now it is not touching any part of the vaginal
wall, it's only touching the uterus because that's the issue. Maybe it
is coming from irritation of the vaginal wall, maybe it's coming from
the uterus. Well, let's see. Is it some, what, did
it pass the cervix?
Well, okay, let's say up to the cervix then, you're right. Anyway,
okay.
So it says like this. נמצא דם על
ראש המוך, Nimtza dam al rosh hamoch, if you find it on
the top of this pad, בידוע שמן המקור הוא, beyadu'a shemin hamakor
hu, so it's coming from the uterus because it didn't touch the
vaginal wall, it went right up as it came to the cervix.
So if there's any blood it's uterine
blood, שמן המקור הוא. shemin hamakor hu. לא נמצא דם
על ראשה, Lo nimtza dam al roshah, if there's no blood on
it, בידוע שמן הצדדים הוא, beyadu'a shemin hatzdadim hu, so it's coming
from the sides and it's vaginal blood and it's therefore not uterine
blood and it's not a problem. Okay, now of course there's a
lot of questions about this like... One. This is not exactly replicating
the experience that she was having, right? I mean, but that's why
that's a good thing because it didn't say if you find blood
on the side of the tubes, then it's okay, right? because that
would be sort of mean it would be harder to prove that
it's not a problem. Here, it says as long as you didn't
find blood on the top of the applicator on the top of
the pad, you're okay. So at least we're sort of being lenient.
But even so, it's still not a good test, like maybe the
sex is bringing on uterine bleeding, but this wasn't an act of
sex,
so there's no blood here. You know, so what does absence of
blood exactly prove if you're not duplicating the circumstances? Okay, so that's
like one question: how does this really prove anything? but that so
whatever that gets discussed. The other issue here is I know it's
trying to help her but right I mean okay but just pointing
out the problem. The other issue here is how frequently does she
have to do the test? In the simple read of this you
do it once and you see okay I see that it's not
a it's not uterine bleeding, no problem, any bleeding is whatever. רש"י
Rashi and תוספות based on an ongoing point in גמרא Gemara speak
about her having to do this test on a regular basis. Like
maybe every time before she is about to have sex or so.
Okay, so that's like a separate issue about that, right? How often
is she doing it? But now we're going to turn to the
question that everybody's asking which is why did she have to wait
till her third husband, right? Do this test earlier. All right, so
let's take a look at where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
But we're not even done yet because there's other factors to consider
to be lenient here.
ומה אם יש לה מכה באותו מקום u-ma im yesh la maka
b'oto makom if she has a wound in that place, תולה במכתה
toleh b'makatah she can assume that it's wound blood, which is important.
Meaning,
meaning, even if, I mean it's not explicit here, but the implication
seems to be that even if there's blood on the top on
the pad and it's coming from the uterus, it could come from
the uterus without
being menstrual uterine bleeding. It could be coming from the uterus because
there's an actual wound in the uterus itself. Okay, which you do
have sometimes. So this is another way of being lenient with this
basic principle and this the importance of this line is not just
for this case of bleeding as a result of sex. This idea,
although addressed in other גמרות, is most explicitly addressed here in this
particular case that has broader application. That if we can assess that
a woman's bleeding is resulting from a wound or most likely resulting
from a wound,
whether in the vagina whether in the uterus, then it is not
a problem and she's not a נידה. niddah. So then the whole
point becomes how do you know? how do you determine? What type
of factors do you consider? right? Is it coming together with pain?
Is the color the same as the color of uterine bleeding? Is
the woman on you know, are you trying to get your הפסק
טהרה hefsek taharah and your שבעה נקיים shiva nekiyim or are you
already טהורה? tehorah? There's like a whole range of different factors which
you use to try to determine these things. But the basic idea
that you that you can be תולה במכה toleh b'maka and if
there's a wound it's a way of discounting, you know, if you
can
make a if you can have a good way of assuming it's
based on the wound is the primary sort of discussion is right
during this line and the discussion the גמרא's Gemara about to have.
And I should say, I should say that possibly even without doing
this I would say even more, it sounds like even if you
did the test and you got a positive and there was blood
on the top of the מוך moch or whatever the pad, but
if you can also determine there's a מכה maka you can discount
it because of the מכה. maka. Yes, it's coming from the uterus,
but it's מכה maka blood coming from the uterus. But then why
test if there's a מכה? maka? Because you might not be able
to determine there's a מכה. maka. I mean, right, if you do
it with a מכה maka added on you wouldn't have to worry
about the test. Okay now I should say by the way that
it's not clear here when you say תולה במכה toleh b'maka there's
two possibilities what it means. The first possibility means she doesn't have
to get divorced from her husband, right? She can assume she can
assume that the sex isn't bringing on נידה niddah blood etc. she
doesn't have to get divorced from her husband. But there's but
there's a next stage of saying and she's not even a נידה.
niddah. Right? Do you understand? Like there's one thing saying well we'll
rely on it enough to say she doesn't have to get divorced.
Are we going to rely on the assumption of the מכה maka
so much to say she's not even a נידה? niddah? But presumably
the answer is yes, because if you're going to say she's a
נידה niddah and it's going to happen pretty regularly, you're not helping
matters much. Okay, but this is the very important category of relying
on a מכה. maka. I will say nowadays when women actually it
does happen when women who bleed at intercourse, so sometimes it's because
of a lack of full rupturing of the hymen and it's so
hymenal bleeding, what happens at the beginning of a marriage, and sometimes
it happens because of irritation or whatever and we basically don't bother
with this whole three times and the test or whatever, we just
go straight into getting a gynecologist, you know, to look and to
assess and so on and to determine if it's מכה maka bleeding,
you know, a straight assessment of it as מכה maka bleeding as
a way of better to
use modern science.
Yes, absolutely. Exactly.
Okay, so that is
so
in the end it all often it really often boils down to
this issue of the מכה. maka.
A lot of things we don't need modern science for.
I know, but this issue about תולה במכה... toleh b'maka... have a
lot to do with rabbis in conversation with doctors. Okay.
Are you going to answer why we don't do this anymore?
Yeah, yeah. אם יש לה וסת. Im yesh lah veset. Now, if
she has a וסת, veset, a regular period, תולה בוסתה. tola b'vestah.
She can make it dependent on her וסת. veset. What does that
mean? It means if let's say this bleeding with sex only occurs
at particular intervals, let's say right around the end of her cycle,
let's say she sees every 28 days, and when she has sex
on day 27 or 26, that's when she'll bleed. So fine, so
don't have sex at day 27 and 26, you can stay married,
you can say that it's, yes, it brings it about, but only
at certain times, other times you don't have to worry about it.
ואם היה דם מכתה משונה מדם ראייתה, v'im hayah dam makatah meshuneh
mi'dam re'iyatah, אינה תולה. einah tolah. Let's say however the bleeding of
the מכה maka is different than the bleeding that she has as
a result of sex, right? The מכה maka bleeding often will tend
to be a brighter red because it's not like I said a
sloughing off of the uterine lining, and let's say the blood that
she gets as a result of sex is a different color. So
then you can't assume that that is מכה maka blood
because it looks different. Now of course the question becomes, do you
have to check? Are you required in your assessment to look at
the colors or not? Or is it only, no, if you find
that the colors are different, that creates a problem, but you don't
have to look. But anyway, what you are seeing here is again,
looking at a constellation of factors and of data to assess whether
we can determine this as מכה maka bleeding or not. And one
of them happens to be the color of the blood. והיא... v'hi...
you want to say something?
I was going to say, just how she feels.
Like I really... Well, we're getting to her a minute. Charlie you
wanted to say something? No? Okay.
So, ונאמנת, v'ne'emenet, now here comes the woman, she is believed, אישה
לומר, ishah lomar, מכה יש לי במקור שממנה דם יוצא, maka yesh
li b'makor she'mimenah dam yotze,
that I actually have a wound in my uterus that is the
source of the blood. How does she know? So presumably she knows
because she somehow has some sensation. Yeah, I can tell something's happening,
I can tell feel, there's a particular cramping or a pain or
something to me feels like that this is—so that's a pretty amazing
thing that just based on her report without any type of medical
assessment or other evidence.
דברי רבי, divrei Rabbi, that's what רבי Rabbi says. רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, דם מכה בא מן המקור
טמא. dam maka ba min hamakor tamei. Actually if it's a wound
and it's in the uterus, it's still טמא. tamei. Now we're going
to see in a minute how far he takes that. Okay. ורבותינו
העידו דם מכה בא מן המקור שהוא טהור. v'raboteinu he'idu dam maka
ba min hamakor she'hu tahor. But the rabbis have testified that no,
even if it comes from the uterus, if it's מכה maka blood,
if it's from a wound, it's טהור. tahor. So now the גמרא
Gemara says מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, this is just a third opinion
backing up רבי. Rabbi. מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what is this debate
about? Now you might say, maybe it's a debate that if you
have blood from the uterus, regardless of whether it is menstrual bleeding
or uterine lining, maybe any blood through the uterus makes a woman
a נדה. niddah But the גמרא Gemara does not take it that
far. It says even רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
is not saying the woman is a נדה. niddah. He's just saying
the blood is טמא. tamei. And you might remember this debate. So
it says מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, אמר עולא, amar Ulla, מקור מקומו
טמא איכא בינייהו. makor mekomo tamei ika beinaihu. What they're debating is
whether the uterus itself just being in the uterus makes the blood
טמא. tamei. Although this is not נדה niddah. blood, it's just מכה
maka blood, wound blood, but is wound blood that has been in
the uterus, is it itself טמא? tamei? But that's for הלכות טומאה
וטהרה, hilchot tumah v'taharah, not for the woman. The woman, even according
to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, is definitely not
a נדה. Niddah She is not having
menstrual bleeding, she is not having blood from the uterine lining. The
only question is, okay, but the blood was in the uterus, is
the blood itself טמא? tamei? But not the woman. So that's not
really our focus, something we've discussed before.
Does that make the mikvah טמא tamei if she went into a...
Make her טמא tamei if she wanted to touch תרומה. terumah. Doesn't
make her טמא tamei as a נדה. niddah Okay, makes her טמא
tamei like she touched it. All right. So now we have this
basic idea though that you can do this test, and this test
is good, and she can also be תולה במכה, tola b'maka, which
is a huge point in הלכות נדה. Yes. Now, but we're still
going to get back to why she didn't do it with the
first husbands yet.
Won't the child be טמא? tamei?
Yeah, he's טמא tamei anyway because the woman is a יולדת. yoledet.
Yeah, she's טמא tamei because the woman is a יולדת. yoledet. If
the child doesn't touch anything? Oh because he came through the fetus?
No, presumably this idea is only blood that was in the uterus,
not other things that were in the uterus. Okay, like placenta or
other liquids that gets discharged from the uterus. All right. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. גמרא Gemara, has a couple of
questions. Now we look at the גמרא's Gemara, analysis. Okay, so first
the גמרא Gemara says like
this, שפופרת אטו מפסר נפסרה לה. shfoferet atu mifsar nifsra lah. It'll
scratch her, assume that you have some type of a wooden tube,
a bamboo tube, that's going to lead to a couple of false
positives or negatives or whatever, anyway, it's going to cause bleeding. אמר
רב פפא בשפופרת של אבר. amar Rav Papa b'shfoferet shel avar. No,
no, no, it's a lead tube, it's a smooth metal,
smooth metal and therefore it's not going to cause scratching or abrasion,
ופיה רצוף לתוכה. u'fih ratzuf l'tochah. The lip is turned inward, so
even the lip won't cause scratching. What? No sharp edge. No sharp
edge, exactly. אמר ליה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן. amar leh Reish Lakish
l'Rabbi Yochanan. Okay, so now we have another question.
ותבדוק עצמה בביאה שלישית של בעל ראשון. v'tivdok atzmah b'viah shlishit shel
ba'al rishon. What everybody is after. What? She had sex time number
three with the husband, why
not... Why not check yourself for the first
guy? אמר ליה Amar lei *Amar leh*, so he said back to
him, לפי שאין כל אצבעות שוות *lefi she'ein kol etzba'ot shavot*.
All fingers are not the same, finger obviously being a euphemism. So
which means that maybe by the second guy it won't be a
problem. So what? So what? So right, so meaning yes, the way
רש"י *Rashi* says it is yes, if she wanted to, she could
do the test by the first guy. But there's a little bit
of a problem. The problem is, the way רש"י *Rashi* says it
is she'd have to do the test every time before she had
sex. The way and maybe she doesn't want to do that. The
way other ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* say it is, if you did the
test and it was a positive, right, then not only can you
not have sex with the first guy, but if you did the
test and it was a positive, you wouldn't be able to get
married to anybody because this test, although we've raised questions, why does
the test prove anything, it's not really replicating circumstances or whatever,
but bracketing all those important questions, it seems like this test is
going to determine once and for all whether she's to be either
totally מותר *mutar* or totally אסור assur, *assur*. So therefore she doesn't
want to risk doing the test in the first guy. So the
question is, you know what, yes, you know, if she wants to
she could do the test with the first guy, but maybe she
doesn't want to do it every time she has sex, or maybe
she doesn't want to do it and risk it being a positive.
She'd rather do it a second time and with the second guy
she doesn't have to bother with the test because with the second
guy maybe that will be different, maybe, you know, the anatomy will
be different and it won't be a problem. So everybody agrees that
if she wants to she can do it with the first guy,
which is why what we do is we just have her, you
know, go to a doctor which instead of doing this test and
determine if it's a מכה maka *makkah*. But here the question is
that if she doesn't want to, why it's legitimate to go to
the second guy without a test. Yes.
Can she just, can they decide to stay married and not have
sex?
I was going to ask. Yeah, I mean in principle yes, I
mean there's a חיוב *chiyuv* of עונה onah *onah* that the husband
owes the wife and, you know, and that the wife is supposed
to also be available to the husband for sex. If they both
agree, then in theory, yes, I mean, you know, question if there's
children and if you've been יוצא *yotzei* פרו ורבו *pru urvu*, whatever,
but you know, halakhically the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* never considers it to
be sort of a tolerable option to consider not having sex. Like
for example, you know, when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* speaks of, earlier
we had a classic גמרא Gemara *Gemara* also in the beginning of
יבמות
*Yevamot* or whatever, that about a woman that
it's a, you know, where it's a risk of life to get
pregnant. Okay, questions about either she's very young or other types of
cases where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* considers it to be a risk
of life to get pregnant. And basically the question is can she
have sex using birth control or does she have sex without birth
control? That's the question in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Nobody ever suggests
well why don't they just not have sex until the risk, until
there's no longer a risk? So that is an important point, you
know, about the centrality of the idea of a marriage, of a
marriage relationship being seen as inseparable.
I understand.
Right. I do understand that. So the basic answer is the basic
answer is yes, it's a possibility if both partners agree, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't you know, doesn't understand that, doesn't understand sort
of, you know, very different from the Christian ideal of a sexless
marriage. The גמרא *Gemara* thinks that basically marriage means that the couple's
having sex.
But you know there's a risk because they may end up having
sex even though they say they don't want to?
Well,
that's a good point too. It's sort of like the woman that
doesn't have a וסת קבוע *veset kavua* according to רבי Rebbi מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* and so on. Yeah, Michael raises a good point too.
Whether the גמרא *Gemara* might not, you know, the גמרא *Gemara* might
say because sex is so central, because just of general appetite and
desire or whatever, maybe we wouldn't allow it because you know we
couldn't you know they they wouldn't they wouldn't be able to restrain
themselves. So it's two reasons I think why the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't
consider it. One, the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't want to consider that phenomenon
at all, and number two, as Michael says, they might, you know,
we might not even be able to trust that they'll be able
to keep to that commitment. Do you want to say something? Those
those...
I mean sex within marriage as a couple thing. It seems to
be
something that will occur in the relationship, right, and it's integral to
it, but also it's possible that it has nothing to do with
the relationship but with the individual, the person who has a sex
drive, and
that doesn't...
Yeah, that's Michael's point.
Well that answers your question about why go to marry somebody else,
like how does that help the relationship, but it does help in
the sense of a person fulfilling their sex drive.
Right, if people can't live a sexless life. Right, that's right, you're
right. I was sort of doing more like a religious ideological point
about sex as part of marriage, and what you and Michael are
saying is yeah, forget that, the individual sex drive we have to
address that reality. Right.
And there's nothing about marriage in here.
Right.
Right. Okay, so let's see. You want to say or?
And the romantic love is really that we think about today, really
comes from the Middle Ages.
Yes and no, that's a larger discussion also in כתובות *Ketubot* and
different statements about marriage. It seems like romantic love
was a little bit more of an ideal in the ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael? *Eretz Yisrael* sources than in the בבלי *Bavli* sources. It's
a larger discussion. Okay, moving on. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this,
okay. So it says ותבדוק עצמה let her check herself בביאה ראשונה
של בעל שלישי B'viah rishona shel ba'al shlishi meaning not let her
but meaning why do we allow her to have sex three times
with husband number three? Now she's been having she's had three different
husbands it's a repeated pattern as soon as husband number three the
first time she bleeds even though he also has a different anatomy
you should say look now we see it's three different anatomies and
she still happens. Why is she allowed to have sex times number
two and three with husband number three? So it says לפי שאין
כוח כוחו שוה Lefi she'ein koach kocho shaveh because not only is
anatomy different but different acts of sex have different types of energy
used and the impact and so on and therefore could bleed one
time and not other times and we're not going to say it's
always a problem unless it happens three times with the same person.
Okay and then if it's all three times and three different people
and so on now we have a universal problem.
Even with the same person it means?
I understand. I get it. At least only so much. ההיא דאתאי
לקמיה דרבי. Hahi d'asai l'kamei d'Rabbi. Now we have one or two
stories. So a woman came in front of
Rabbi. אמר ליה Amar lei, anyway she said to him excuse me
he said I'm sorry right. So this woman came to Rabbi. אמר
ליה לאבדן Amar lei l'Avdan he said to Avdan his like assistant
זיל בעתה. Zil ba'asah. He said go to the back of the
room and then scare her. Okay. אזל בעתה Azal ba'asah he scared
her okay he surprised her ונפל מינה כחרות דם V'nafal minah k'charos
dam and a little glob of blood fell out of her. The
shock caused some glob of blood to fall out of her. אמר
רבי נתרפא זו. Amar Rabbi nitrapa zo. Oh now she's been healed.
So he assumed that this was a result not of menstrual bleeding
but some type of a מכה maka some thing in her some
body mass was causing blood was being hit in the act of
sex and irritated the act of sex and somehow he figured that
out and figured out how to heal her. Okay so I question
why she was coming before. No
she it's implicit she explained the problem. But the interesting thing is
not just that he assessed that it was based on a מכה
maka but that he somehow figured out exactly what the problem was
or how to solve it. Okay hiccups right exactly. Okay now we're
going to have another case.
אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel ההיא איתתא דאתאי לקמיה דמר שמואל. hahi itesa
d'asai l'kamei d'Mar Shmuel. Now a woman came in front of Shmuel.
אמר ליה לרב דימי בר יוסף Amar lei l'Rav Dimi bar Yosef
so he said to Rav Dimi bar Yosef זיל בעתה zil ba'asah
go scare her. אזל בעתה Azal ba'asah he scared her surprised her
ולא נפל מינה ולא מידי v'lo nafal minah v'lo midi nothing fell
out of her. אמר שמואל זו ממלאה ונופצת היא.
Amar
Shmuel zu memaleh v'nofetzes hi.
This is a woman that fills up and then sort of lets
out blood. וכל הממלאה ונופצת אין לה תקנה. V'chol hamemaleh v'nofetzes ein
lah takanah. And therefore there's no help for her because it's not
based on a מכה maka it must be based on the fact
that uterine bleeding does actually somehow triggered by the act of sex.
So which is also a very funny argument the opposite way. Okay
your little experiment didn't work. Maybe we should still try other things
we should try the thing with the tube we should try other
ways of assessing if it's a מכה so it's a little bit
of funny that he went to the opposite extreme once this little
test didn't work. Okay ההיא דאתאי לקמיה דרבי יוחנן. Hahi d'asai l'kamei
d'Rabbi Yochanan. Now a woman came in front of Yochanan דכל אימת
דהוה סלקא מטבילת מצוה הוי חזיא דמא. D'chol eimas d'hava salka mitvilas
mitzvah hava chazya dama. So we said one problem is if you
always bleed as a result of sex how do you ever have
sex if you assume it's נדה bleeding? This woman got her period
as soon as she went to the מקוה. Mikvah. Now nowadays unfortunately
that's not so rare because now that we have the demand seven
clean days for every woman and then there's normally a four or
five day waiting period anyway you start to wait till the blood
stops twelve days or whatever some women have very short cycles and
can bleed soon after going to the מקוה. Mikvah. Anyway it was
less common in the time of the in this time because in
this time they weren't demanding seven clean days. Anyway here's a woman
that basically
bled as soon as going to the מקוה Mikvah so then how's
she ever going to be with her husband? So what happens? So
she comes to Rabbi Yochanan דכל אימת דהוה סלקא מטבילת מצוה הוי
חזיא דמא D'chol eimas d'hava salka mitvilas mitzvah hava chazya dama whenever
she got out of the מקוה Mikvah she saw blood. אמר לה
Amar lah he said to her שמא דיבת עירך עלתה בך. Shema
divas ircha alsah bach. Maybe the gossip of your city has come
up upon you. Meaning basically people are giving you an עין הרע
ayin hara somehow they're jealous of you and your husband or whatever
it is and that עין הרע ayin hara is making you bleed
whenever you leave whenever you get out of the מקוה. Mikvah. So
לכי והיחבאי על גבי הנהר. Lechi v'heichave'i al gabei hanahar. So how
do you translate דיבת? divas? דיבת Divas is a gossip as a
דיבה diba almost.
Yeah Rashi gives you the etymology. So
anyway so he says maybe it's an עין הרע ayin hara so
how do you deal with it? Don't let people see you've gone
to the מקוה. Mikvah. Apparently people would know when people were coming
back from the מקוה Mikvah they saw people coming out of the
מקוה Mikvah or something. So what do you do? Go to a
river go have טבילה tevilah do your טבילה tevilah in a river
and go be with your husband near the river. And therefore nobody
will see that you've gone to the מקוה Mikvah and they won't
cast an עין הרע ayin hara to you. Okay fascinating. Yep.
So what they're saying is that all these three stories show that
they believe that there's some psycho- social or stress-related aspect?
Well, I'm not sure about the thing with the mass of blood.
Yeah, they're saying the giving of a shock, it's stress-related somehow.
Yeah, but then the mass falls out.
I know, but those biological reactions occur due to psychological. Oh, I
see. Okay. All right.
Okay. That's interesting. Okay. Then they might, איכא דאמרי ika d'amri some
said אמר לה amar lah he said to her, צלי וחברתייך, tzili
v'chavrateych, so maybe here here's a better assessment of human nature. He
says, you know what? Tell your friends that things aren't so great.
Things right exactly, tell your friends that this is happening to you,
that you're always bleeding as soon as you come out of the
מקווה mikvah and you're never able to be with your husband. Why?
כי היכי דתהוו עלך לחכיס, ki hichei d'tehavu alach l'hachis, כי היכי
דתהוו עלך לחכיס, ki hichei d'tehavu alach l'hachis, the same way they
gave an עין הרע ayin hara before, now they'll feel compassionate for
you and that'll remove the עין הרע ayin hara because they won't,
they just felt, you know, jealous of you. Now that they're hearing
that you're never with your husband, they'll feel less jealous of you
and you won't have the עין הרע ayin hara and then it'll
be better. Okay. תוספות, in a more cynical approach towards human nature,
says that you should tell your friends that you're having a lot
of bleeding because we learned before that women who bleed a lot
have a lot of kids. So then they'll be very jealous of
all the of how much you bleed and that'll prevent you from
bleeding. So a little more cynical approach, they're not going to have
compassion, they'll get jealous about something else so that'll counteract this effect.
The healing power of the
of עין הרע, ayin hara, right, as long as you can manipulate
the עין הרע, ayin hara, well תוספות is manipulating the עין הרע.
ayin hara. עין טוב, ayin tov, right. Do you want to say
something? Okay, fine.
Anyway, actually I have one question, you know, regarding the woman and
two different husbands and all that, but I mean were there any
עצות eitzot that, you know, that the man can do?
Like that wasn't considered? Yeah, so right, thank you for for for
playing the role of רבקה Rivka in her absence, right. The assumption
of course is that it's all the husband, the woman's problem. Now,
if it's three different husbands and it's all, that's that's the evidence.
But even the first time the assumption was it was the woman
and not the man and, you know, that, yeah, so that's a
good that's a good point, that we are not focus we are
again ignoring that. Okay, now the גמרא, איכא דאמרי ika d'amri third
version, אמר לה, amar lah, גלי לחברתייך כי היכי דליבעו עלך רחמי.
gali l'chavrateych ki hichei d'libo alach rachamei. So there you go, the
third version everybody does believe in, you know, in people's compassion. Tell
your friends and they'll actually pray for you and proactively. דתניא, d'tanya,
וטמא טמא יקרא, v'tamay tamay yikra, by the נזיר? Nazir? No, by
the מצורע Metzora he calls out that he's
טמא. tamay. צריך להודיע צערו לרבים tzarich l'hodia tza'aro l'rabim he has
to inform people about his state, ורבים מבקשים עליו רחמים v'rabim mevakshim
alav rachamim and people will pray for him. So here too, if
people know how hard you're having it, they'll pray for you and
hopefully that will reverse it. So different ways of solving these problems,
right, medical, psycho-social, you know, תפילה tefillah and so on. אמר רב
יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, הוה עובדא בפומבדיתא hava uvda b'Pumbedita there was
a case in פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, and maybe about the case about sex,
not the case about I don't know the מקווה, mikvah, ואיתסי v'itassi
and the woman was healed. Maybe it is a case of the
מקווה. mikvah. Anyway, so maybe this happened, people prayed for her, whatever
the case was, and she was healed. אמר רב יוסף אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב. amar Rav Yosef amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. That
is now the end of ראה מחמת תשמיש, ra'ah machamat tashmish, which
is a critical discussion primarily for the issue about, and what today
what do we say? About assume the מקום, makom, we have her
go to a doctor and we figure out that
the woman who bleeds at the time of going to the מקווה.
mikvah.
Wait a minute, that's we we we try to figure manipulate that
other ways, see what's what other ways. Okay. Now we move on,
so that's the end of that. Now we move on to really,
really regular practical הלכות נידה hilchos Niddah and perhaps the most important
line of all of contemporary הלכות נידה hilchos Niddah that we've now
been through over two months in this מסכת, masechet, we're going to
see right now and I would actually say as I've said that
in the next two דף or whatever you're going to have more
הלכות נידה hilchos Niddah packed in than we have in the whole
מסכת, masechet, practical הלכות נידה. hilchos Niddah. So let's take a look.
אמר רב יוסף אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yosef amar
Rav Yehuda amar Rav, התקין רבי בשדות. hitkin Rebbi basadot. רבי Rebbi,
made a תקנה, takkanah, an edict in the fields, or some have
the גרסא girsa if you look on the side בשבזית, b'Shavzit, which
is a name of a place, meaning in a place where people
say the mentioning of the place is because it was a place
where people were not so literate, were not so aware of הלכה,
halakhah. they weren't so good, the women, at tracking when they were
bleeding, when they were נידה, Niddah, when it was not during their
נידה Niddah period, when it was a זבה. Zavah. So that's like
the backdrop, that women might not be sure are they a נידה,
Niddah, are they a זבה? Zavah? One of the reasons you're not
sure, besides that maybe you're just not keeping good track, is because
if you don't know the different colors, right, so you might bleed
on day one and you think you're a נידה, Niddah, where actually
that was that wasn't really a red color and really you only
became a נידה Niddah on day two. So then when you bleed
later on day seven, what you think is day seven, you, or
it's a
כותי Cuthi thing almost.
Right, whatever. You know, but or let's
no, let's make it the other way, the other way is easier.
You bleed on day one and you discount it, you think it's
not a problem. You only start counting on day two. So then
when you're bleeding on day seven you think your day seven, you
think that you're still a נידה, Niddah, but really it's day eight
and you're now already in זבות zavut mode and so on. So
if you're either just not paying close attention or if it's hard
to distinguish between the the colors of what are the reds that
are a problem or not, you can easily get off track. And
so the backdrop is is that people might not be aware where
they are in their cycle and whether they're a נידה niddah or
a זבה. zavah. So what תקנה takanah did he make? So רבי,
Rebbi if you bleed one day, תשבו שבעה והוא, teshvu shiv'ah vehu,
you have to wait that day that you bled and six more
days because that's the maximum it could be. If it's a זבה
zavah you only need one day. If it's a נידה niddah then
it's a seven including the day that you bled. שניים, shnayim, if
you bled two days, תשבו שבעה והן, teshvu shiv'ah vehain, then those
two days plus six. Same reason. Why two plus six? If you're
a זבה zavah it would only require one day. If you're a
נידה niddah it should be seven days starting from day one, so
it should be two plus five. But could be that the first
day was זבה zavah bleeding and the second day was the end
of the זבה zavah cycle, the second day was the beginning of
the נידה niddah cycle. So if the second day is the beginning
of the נידה niddah cycle, you need six days after the first
day, after the second day. Is that clear? Yes, sort of? Okay.
So that's תשבו שבעה והן teshvu shiv'ah vehain as I have my
mark here. Now, שלושה, shlosha, if you bled three days, תשבו שבעה
נקיים, teshvu sheva neki'im, then you have to assume that you're a
זבה zavah because maybe you would have said those three days are
all נידה niddah bleeding and I only need four more days and
I can even bleed straight during those four days. But no, you
don't know where you are in your cycle. You might be in
your זבה zavah period. Three days in a row makes you זבה
גדולה, zavah gedolah, now you need שבעה נקיים. sheva neki'im. That was
רבי's Rebbi תקנה. takanah.
That's only בשדות bisodot though.
Number one, it's only בשדות, bisodot, so some people, some argue that
the תקנה takanah was never universal, some say it was, but some
say it was never universal. Number one, and number two is this
is the maximum that you would have to do if you were
having a reasonable concern, a rational concern, which would never have to
wait שבעה נקיים sheva neki'im unless you bled three days consecutively because
anything less than three days consecutively would never make you a זבה
גדולה. zavah gedolah. That was רבי's Rebbi תקנה. takanah. That made sense
and maybe it
was limited, maybe it was universal, that was רבי's Rebbi תקנה. takanah.
Now we get רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira that takes it to the
next level. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, says רבי זירא, Rabbi
Zeira, בנות ישראל החמירו על עצמן, Benot Yisrael hikmiru al atzman, the
Jewish women have been strict upon themselves שאפילו רואות טיפת דם כחרדל,
she'afilu ro'ot tipat dam kachardal, even if they see a drop of
blood as small as a mustard seed, which is very, very tiny,
and some ראשונים, Rishonim just in case you didn't get the point,
say כחרדל ואפילו פחות מכאן. kachardal va'afilu pachot mikan. Okay, as small
as a mustard seed or even less, even if you saw the
tiniest drop of blood, יושבת עליה שבעה נקיים. yoshevet aleha sheva neki'im.
You have to wait שבעה נקיים. sheva neki'im. Now why? It makes
absolutely no sense. There is never a time where you will see
one drop of blood and have to do שבעה נקיים. sheva neki'im.
Either you're נידה niddah and you need seven days but they don't
have to be clean days, or it's a זבה zavah and only
you need one clean day for one drop of blood. And that's
why he said even the tiniest drop because if you saw a
big drop maybe you'd say well maybe it's really three days of
blood that have collected inside my body and haven't come out until
now. No, even the tiniest drop. There's no logic why you should
treat you as a זבה גדולה zavah gedolah and still שבעה נקיים.
sheva neki'im. So why do we do it? So תוספות and the
ראשונים some try to say that it is a type of a-
there's one scenario where a drop of blood will demand שבעה נקיים.
sheva neki'im. What's the case? About a woman who is a זבה
zavah counting שבעה נקיים sheva neki'im and in the middle of those
שבעה נקיים sheva neki'im she sees a drop of blood. In that
case she has to start all over again and do seven. So
there's one scenario where a drop of blood will lead to שבעה
נקיים sheva neki'im and therefore we're treating everything like that. More simply
I think that this is part of the general approach which very
often is dominant in אשכנז, Ashkenaz, but here we're seeing even in
the גמרא, which is called, which I call the keep it simple
stupid approach, which is the חומרא chumra approach, which is rather than
dealing with all these distinctions we'll just apply the strictest law across
the board. Now to some degree רבי Rebbi already did that. He
said when you bleed three times then wait שבעה נקיים sheva neki'im
regardless of where you are, that's the strictest law. But still רבי
Rebbe has too many distinctions. So he gets this way: one day
is one plus six, two days is two plus six, three it's
שבעה נקיים, sheva neki'im, right? Let's just make it simple. So you
know where you're going to make it simple is you're going to
say you're going to take the hybrid of נידה niddah and a
זבה. zavah. What's the story of נידה? niddah? Even one drop of
blood makes a woman a נידה niddah and demands seven days. Not
שבעה נקיים sheva neki'im but seven days. So the strictest aspect of
נידה niddah is even one drop of blood. A זבה zavah is
usually three days. נידה niddah is even one single blood. So you
take the strictest part of נידה, niddah, we combine it with the
strictest part of זבה, zavah, which is when a woman is a
זבה, zavah, שבעה נקיים. sheva neki'im. And now every woman is effectively
a hybrid נידה niddah זבה. zavah. She has a drop of blood
even though it's נידה niddah blood and what do we do is
we apply the זבה zavah laws and we do the שבעה נקיים.
sheva neki'im. And that seems to be where this comes from. It's
like, okay, we're just going to make everything the same law. We're
not going to worry about differences, נידה niddah זבה. zavah. We're going
to take the strict aspect of נידה, niddah, one drop, the strict
aspect of זבה, zavah, שבעה נקיים, sheva neki'im, and that's what we're
going to do nowadays.
But why is this attributed to בנות ישראל? Benot Yisrael?
So that's the question. What does that mean that it's sort of
בנות ישראל? Benot Yisrael? You know some people nowadays
say women's empowerment, oh yeah they say. Right. So one thing,
there's a cynical thing, there's oh yeah, you want to be so
strict and then you blame it on the women. But,
but there is- and I will- but there are others that say
like Michael said, that in the society, and this is interesting to
think in general because we actually have found and I mentioned before
when we did פולטת poletet that there, you know, according to the
גמרא every now and then there would be a need to wait
before you start the שבעה נקיים, sheva neki'im, but according to מנהג
minhag. that developed in אשכנז, Ashkenaz, which clearly developed at the grassroots,
was not from the Rabbis. was to always wait five days before
counting the seven, sometimes they would wait seven days.
They would wait five days, five days before—go back—five days of פולטת.
poletet. So a woman starts bleeding, she waits five days before counting
the seven days. That's the way we do it nowadays. There were
some מנהגים minhagim which were seven days and then the seven, and
this was coming from the grassroots, not from the rabbis. And some
people have speculated that it might have been an early form of
birth control, right? If you wait till you go to the מקוה,
mikveh, what?
So especially
if you wait seven and seven, get past the fertile period. Ooh,
wait.
That's exactly, you hit it exactly.
No, it depends where you are in the—no, the seven and seven,
not the five and seven. Seven and seven, depending on what a
woman's cycle is, could be that.
14, 15, and 16.
Depends on how long the cycle is. Depends woman by woman. Anyway,
the other point is, which Michael said, forget the birth control point,
is that it's also, you know, this is the one area where
a woman says I'm טמאה teme'ah and the husband has to live
with it. So, you know, a certain amount of women empowering women
in the sexual relationship to say no. Okay, now, so that could
be that's a possible backdrop to that. I will say though that
it doesn't—it's not left at saying בנות ישראל, benot Yisrael, because if
it's left at saying בנות ישראל, benot Yisrael, it sounds like if
they don't want to be מחמיר machmir and it's going to be
left as a חומרא chumra and we'll see an indication of that
right now. But within the גמרא, you will see not today, but
tomorrow, that it moves from being treated as a חומרא chumra that
developed from בנות ישראל benot Yisrael to being treated as a תקנה
takanah that was embraced by the rabbis. You know, sort of that
the rabbis came and they gave their backing to it and made
it a תקנה takanah and so on, and we'll get to that
second stage of the development tomorrow. Yes.
A בת ישראל, bat Yisrael, a born Jewish woman.
Yes. חרדל? chardal?
Okay.
Yes, I don't think that that distinction is made, especially when we
move to the next stage of having this transformed into a rabbinic,
you know, type of a position.
Simply the smallest seed? Yeah. I'm stunned. Why? That is one of
the most famous quotes in the—I know, I know.
I mentioned that before, that mustard seed, if you have faith in
me as a mustard—whatever. So that's clearly a clear metaphor for an
extremely infinitesimal, infinitesimal amount. Anyway, yes.
I have a question. Yes. Since when do בנות ישראל benot Yisrael
have any impact on Jewish הלכה?
halakhah Well, if they're the ones that are keeping it!
Is there another example other than this where
there was a בנות ישראל?
benot Yisrael? That's what I'd like to know.
Well, what my mother does in the kitchen. Exactly.
That, but what Rachel means that has somehow been, you know, sort
of canonized and embodied in הלכה. halakhah Oh, this is the way
the women are doing it.
It's being very much an argument.
Yeah, yeah, but that's not what Rachel meant by בנות ישראל. benot
Yisrael. Okay, well I'm saying is there
a legal precedent that basically eradicates a ton of discussion
of making distinctions where things would really be
more
lenient and practically allow if the attention—I mean, it upends the entire
premise
that
this עונה that a woman is entitled to is something she actually
wants.
Well, okay. That's if you go back to sort of my speculation
about where this is coming from. But you are correct that the,
you know, on the one hand Dov is certainly correct that how
הלכה halakhah has been practiced has had a huge impact on sort
of the norms of הלכה halakhah and it's not all based on
the books. And very often when the הלכה halakhah. is in the
domain of women, like נדה or כשרות kashrut or whatever, that has
had an impact. And when certain areas of הלכה halakhah are in
the domain of men, their practice has had an impact,
particularly in any—I'm sorry, I'm going to answer you. Particularly in אשכנז,
Ashkenaz, I'd say in אשכנז Ashkenaz more than in ספרד, Sepharad, the
way it was practiced, even when it veers from the way it
is on the books, often has a huge impact on the sort
of parameters of הלכה. halakhah But in terms of your question, do
you have in the גמרא a case where women's practice sort of
actually establishes הלכה halakha. in like this? I don't think so. I
think this is the only occurrence of that. And we are going
to see that it doesn't get left at that, that gets sort
of backed by the rabbis, but but I think this
is the only occurrence of that. Yeah, but but could—could בנות ישראל
benot Yisrael have הקילו hekellu על עצמן? al atzman?
Well, right.
I—is this a statement about a woman's voice or is it a
statement about we love חומרות chumrot any time we see them?
Yeah, well you can't be מיקל mekel more than the—more than the
law itself. What you do find in the גמרא is when there's
an ambiguity to the law, you can rely on the people's practice
to determine what the law is if there's an ambiguity, even if
their practice is more lenient. But if it's known that the law—there's
a bottom line to the law, you can't violate it based on
practice. But yes, I—I think—I think you're right. Always it's easier to
be more מחמיר machmir than to be more מיקל. mekel. And this
is—I don't think it's a—stay—I think it's a pretty much a good
foreshadowing of a lot of, you know, the of as I said
particularly in אשכנז, Ashkenaz, the reality of חומרות chumrot of practice that
then change הלכה halakha norms, and particularly in the area of חומרות,
chumrot, you know, more often than in
קולות, kulot, although in
אשכנז Ashkenaz sometimes...
I heard Professor Elman suggest that there might have been some Persian
influence.
Yes, but the thing is that this is in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
as well, it's not limited to the בבלי. And רבי זירא, Rebbe
Zeira, isn't
רבי זירא, Rebbe Zeira,
he was in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael.
He was, wasn't he in בבל?
Bavel I'm not good at that.
But anyway, רבי Rebbe, was certainly in...
Well, רבי, רבי'ס תקנה, Rebbe's Takanah, yeah. And anyway, but I think
that anyway it's in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi as well. So ירושלמי Yerushalmi
in ברכות Brachot actually that we're about to get to, you know,
says in the law of הלכה פסוקה, Halakha Psuka, and this is
one of the evidences where it moves out of בנות ישראל B'not
Yisrael and becomes sort of, you know, rabbinically backed. The ירושלמי as
far as I remember does not have it as בנות ישראל, B'not
Yisrael, it has it as like... אנן, anon,
yeah, that from what I remember it has it as הלכה פסוקה
Halakha Psuka that in the גמרא in ברכות Brachot that if it
repeats it says בנות ישראל טיפת דם יושבת עליה שבעה נקיים. B'not
Yisrael Tipat Dam Yoshevet Aleiha Shva Nekiya. So I'm skeptical about this
being sort of... there definitely were a lot of menstrual taboos in
בבל Bavel, amongst the Persians, there's no question about that, but I
don't think this is particularly linked to that.
Yes, רבי זירא Rebbe Zeira was born in בבל, made עליה. Aliyah.
Ah, okay, I thought he was ארץ ישראל. Okay, so let's keep
on going. The גמרא says like
this: אדריה רבא לרב שמואל. Adrei Rava le-Rav Shmuel. So רבא Rava
took רב שמואל Rav Shmuel ודרש vedarash and gave the following דרשה,
drasha, meaning he wanted רב שמואל Rav Shmuel to now proclaim it,
okay? That's why he took רב שמואל, Rav Shmuel, he was his
megaphone. And he said: קשתה שני ימים והשלישי הפילה. Kashta shnei yamim
ve-hashlishi hipila. If a woman has childbirth pains for two days with
seeing blood, and on the third day has a miscarriage,
then תשב שבעה נקיים. teshev shva nekiyim. She has to assume she's
a זבה. zava. Why? קסבר אין קישוי לנפל. Kasavar ein kishul u-nefel.
Number one, why do you say that the childbirth pains even with
זבה zava bleeding discount זבה zava bleeding? You're going to get that
before. Okay, so no, says that would be if it was a
live birth, but if it is a miscarriage, then the birth doesn't
allow you
to
discount the bleeding. So that's אין קישוי לנפל, ein kishul u-nefel, so
you cannot discount the bleeding because in the end it was a
miscarriage. And how about the fact that she didn't bleed on the
third day? No, אי אפשר לפתיחת הקבר בלא דם. i efshar l'ptichat
hakever belo dam. A woman doesn't miscarry without, or the uterus doesn't
open in a miscarriage without blood coming out. So even if you
didn't see blood the third day, how did you do that with
being miscarried? I don't know. Anyway, you have to assume blood, and
therefore this woman has bled three times, because it was a miscarriage
she doesn't get out of the bleeding with the pains, and she's
a זבה, zava, שבעה נקיים. shva nekiyim. That was the דרשה. drasha.
Okay, stuff we've seen before. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא, Amar lei
Rav Pappa le-Rava, so רב פפא Rav Pappa said to רבא, Rava,
מאי איריא קשתה שני ימים? mai irya kashta shnei yamim? Why do
you have to give us an area that she is bleeding already
two days before? אפילו משהו בעלמא, afillu mashehu b'alma, even if she
just bled once during the
miscarriage, once is enough to make שבעה נקיים. shva nekiyim. דאמר רבי
זירא, De-amar Rebbe Zeira, בנות ישראל החמירו על עצמן שאפילו רואות טיפת
דם כחרדל יושבות עליה שבעה נקיים. B'not Yisrael hichmiru al atzman she-afillu
ro'ot tipat dam ke-chardal yoshevot aleiha shva nekiyim. So he said there's
this practice of seven clean days even with one drop of blood,
why are you now talking in here that she is halakhically bleeding?
So now, right, well, right, you see a move of רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, remember the players here, רבא Rava and רב פפא. Rav
Pappa. רבא Rava is... and let's see what רבא's Rava answer is.
אמר ליה, Amar Lei, רבא Rava said back to him, אמינא לך
איסורא, amina lach issura, I'm talking to you about something that's really
אסור, about real הלכה. halakha. Real הלכה halakha, requires three days during
the זבה zava period. את אמרת מנהגא, at amrat minhaga, you're quoting
רבי זירא Rebbe Zeira about some מנהג. minhag, היכא דאחמיר אחמיר היכא
דלא אחמיר לא אחמיר. hecha d'achmir achmir, hecha d'lo achmir lo achmir.
Where they have the חומרא chumra they have it, where they don't
have the חומרא chumra they don't have it. That's a מנהג, minhag,
we're not talking מנהג, minhag, we're talking הלכה. halakha Okay, but what
you see is that רבא Rava is sort of insisting this is
מנהג, it's not universal, and רב פפא Rav Pappa is saying, quoting
it like אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rebbe Zeira, as if it became
a rabbinic statement, as if it became הלכה, Halacha and we are
going to see in tomorrow's דף that this is exactly what happens,
that רב פפא Rav Pappa is a key part of this process
of taking רבי זירא's Rebbe Zeira statement and transforming it into universal
הלכה and pushing רבי זירא's Rebbe Zeira thing. So here רבא Rava
is resisting it, but we're going to see the end of this
story tomorrow. Let's see a little bit further.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, תבעוה לינשא ונתפייסה. tavuha li linasei v'nispaysa. If
a man said to a woman who he was married to, קידושין,
kiddushin, but they have yet to live together, that's it, let's start
living together tomorrow, let's have the נישואין, nisuin, the חופה chuppah tomorrow,
which just means they actually start living together, a married life, okay?
So then and
she agreed, ונתפייסה, v'nispaysa, she was sort of persuaded. צריכה שתשב שבעה
נקיים. Tsricha she-teshev shva nekiyim. She has to wait שבעה נקיים shva
nekiyim after the man said, you know, sort of surprised her, said
let's get married tomorrow. Why? Because the גמרא basically assumes that the
sexual excitement and the change sort of suddenly, it wasn't like they
were planning their wedding or whatever, you know, and that sexual excitement,
arousal causes some spotting. Some people have speculated that this is a
sort of transference of the male experience of sexual excitement can cause
seminal emission, that they may have thought that women's sexual excitement could
cause some spotting.
And therefore she has to wait שבעה נקיים. shva nekiyim.
Even if she saw no blood, she still has to wait? Yes,
presumably. So she checked herself
out.
So there's some discussion in the ראשונים if she checked immediately does
it address it, but the general assumption sort of like the דם
בתולים as it evolves is even without blood. Now by the way,
notice שבעה נקיים. Shiva Neki'im. So what we've done here is we've
built on Rabbi Zeira, tiny drop of blood שבעה נקיים, Shiva Neki'im,
to a case where you didn't even see blood.
You didn't even see blood!
You don't even need the blood and you can have the שבעה
נקיים. Shiva Neki'im. So you sort of see how, and you know
it sort of ties into the דם בתולים of yesterday where maybe
things that otherwise wouldn't have been problematic blood or whatever, all of
a sudden everything requires שבעה נקיים. Shiva Neki'im. Okay, so you see
very quickly how this is evolving. Now רבינא Ravina יסב ליה לבריה.
Isiv Lei Livrei. רבינא Ravina was marrying off his son, בי רבי
חנינא Bei Rabbi Chanina to the daughter of Rabbi Chanina. אמר ליה,
Amar Lei, סבר ליה מר למכתב כתובה לארבעה יום דארבעה יום ארבעה,
Savar Lei Mar Lemichtav Ketuvah L'Arba'a Yom D'Arva Yom Arba'a, should we
write the כתובה Ketuvah for four days from now, which means have
them actually have the חופה Chuppah four days from now? אמר ליה,
Amar Lei, אין. In. He says, yeah, good idea.
כי מטא לארבעה, Ki Meta L'Arba'a, when it came the fourth day,
נטרן ארבעה אחריני. Natran Arba'a Acharini. He said you know what, we
have to wait four more days for the חופה. Chuppah. יהבי שבעה
יומי. Yahavi Shiva Yomei. So wait seven days, I guess day four
plus four days makes seven... בתר ההוא יומא, Batar Hahu Yoma, after
that day, after day he said we have to wait more probably
after the first day because you know day four plus four days,
seven days. Anyway, אמר ליה, Amar Lei, מאי האי? Mai Hai? Why
are you waiting so long? We said we were going to do
it on Wednesday, what are you waiting four more days or seven
more days or whatever? אמר ליה, Amar Lei, לא סבר ליה מר
להא דאמר רבא? Lo Savar Lei Mar L'Ha D'Amar Rava? Don't you
hold what Rava said? דאמר רבא, D'Amar Rava, תבעוה לינשא ונתפייסה צריכה
לישב שבעה נקיים. Tvu'ah Linasei Venitpayasa Tzericha Leishev Shiva Neki'im. That once
you sort of said let's have the חופה, Chuppah, you need to
wait שבעה נקיים Shiva Neki'im because you can't do it immediately. אמר
ליה, Amar Lei, אימור דאמר רבא בגדולה דחזיא דמא. Eimur D'Amar Rava
B'Gedolah D'Chazya Dama. When would Rava say this? By a woman who
is you know who has hit puberty, that she has her menstrual
period, so maybe she had it because of the excitement of this.
This also echoes, is an echo of what we've learned yesterday about
the דם בתולים about where is the woman, how old is she,
do we have to be concerned about menstrual bleeding? אבל בקטנה, Aval
B'Ktanah, this case where your daughter is a minor, underage girl... okay
we can all you know have a risk of... okay that's a
big problem, but in this case where your daughter's an underage girl,
דלא חזיא דמא, D'Lo Chazya Dama, that she has not even had
her period yet, מי אמר? Mi Amar? He would never have said
it, we don't have to wait seven days. That means she's you
know this young girl has never even had her period. אמר ליה,
he said back, פירש שמע רבא. Peresh Shma Rava. Rava explicitly said,
לא שנא גדולה ולא שנא קטנה. Lo Shna Gedolah V'Lo Shna Ktanah.
It doesn't matter if she's an adult or a minor. גדולה טעמא
מאי? Gedolah Ta'ama Mai? Why by a גדולה Gedolah do you have
to wait שבעה נקיים Shiva Neki'im after you sort of announce you're
going to have the חופה? Chuppah? משום דמחמדה, Mishum D'Michamda, because she
has sexual desire and that might lead to some bleeding. קטנה נמי
מחמדה. Ktanah Nami Michamda. Even by a minor she also has desire.
Which is just fine and shocking because you know A, besides the
fact that a קטנה Ktanah isn't getting her menstrual period so there's
not a concern about that, it's the also the assumption about the
sexual desire on the קטנה, Ktanah, you know which again sort of
ties in and this really is you know the point that Rifka
has been making, ties into the reality that they are marrying and
having sex with with these little girls and now also assuming that
the girls are sort of like willing participants of it and having
similar types of sexual desire. So I think we will have to
end here but we'll continue on very other relevant הלכה continued tomorrow.